Guide to the Phi Delta Kappa, Delta Chapter (Stanford University), Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Phi Delta Kappa, Delta Chapter (Stanford University), records
1909-1965
SC0213
Phi Delta Kappa. Delta Chapter (Stanford University).
4.5 Linear feet
These records include memberships lists, constitution and bylaws, correspondence, minutes, account books, newsletters, publications, and materials from several biennial meetings of the national council. In addition to correspondence between Stanford chapter leaders and their membership, there is correspondence with national leaders and with other collegiate chapters. Correspondents include E. P. Cubberley, John D. Houser, Frank A. Scofield, Erwin E. Lewis, Julian E. Butterworth, Albert M. Davis, Emmett Ellis, Walter E. Morgan, and John R. Nichols.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1979.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Phi Delta Kappa, Honorary Fraternity, was organized May 23, 1911 at Stanford University. It is a chapter of Pi Kappa Mu, which was organizaed May 4, 1909. Faculty members at the time of the founding of the Delta chapter at Stanford were Ellwood P. Cubberley, Percy E. Davidson, Rufus Clarence Bentley, and Lewis Madison Terman. The nature and purpose of the club as stated in their constitution reads: Phi Delta Kappa shall be a fraternity founded upon educational principles and supporting the highest educational ideals. It shall exist for the purpose of mutual help of men of sound moral character and of recognized professional training and ability interested in the scientific study of education. It shall foster research both in and out of the university and shall ever uphold the great truth that the noblest and most efficient service to the state is that rendered through the education of her children.
Description of the Collection
These records, dating from 1909 to 1965, include membership lists, constitution and bylaws, correspondence, minutes, account books, newsletters, publications, and materials from several biennial meetings of the national council. In addition to correspondence between Stanford chapter leaders and their membership, there is correspondence with national leaders and with other collegiate chapters. Correspondents include E. P. Cubberley, John D. Houser, Frank A. Scofield, Erwin E. Lewis, Julian E. Butterworth, Albert M. Davis, Emmett Ellis, Walter E. Morgan, and John R. Nichols.
The original order of the correspondence in Box 1 has not been substantially altered. It was removed from the letter-boxes and refoldered; consequently there is some overlapping of dates. The alpha reference is not always to the letter writer, but may reflect the state, other college chapters, or the national office. The correspondence in Box 3 was resorted and is filed alphabetically by author, with the exception of several letters pertaining to “Lambda Chapter” at Berkeley, filed under L.
Access Terms
Butterworth, Julian Edward, 1884-; Cubberley, Ellwood Patterson, 1868-1941; Davis, Albert Mott.; Ellis, Emmett.; Houser, J. David.; Lewis, Erwin E.; Morgan, Walter Emmett, 1896-; Nichols, John R.; Phi Delta Kappa. Delta Chapter (Stanford University).; Scofield, Frank A.; College students.; Education--Societies, etc.; Student activities.
Collection Contents
- Records
  - Introductory information, constitution, and newsletters of Phi Delta Kappa, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and financial records, A through H, 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and financial records, I through S, 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and financial records, S through Z, 1911-1913 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, A through G, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, H through N, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, O through Z, 1911-1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chron. file containing journals, newsletters, programs and some related correspondence, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Chron. file containing journals, newsletters, programs and some related correspondence, 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chron. file containing journals, newsletters, programs and some related correspondence, 1917-1922 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chron. file containing journals, newsletters, programs and some related correspondence, 1923-1924 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Chron. file containing journals, newsletters, programs and some related correspondence, 1925-1936 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - San Francisco alumni newsletters, 1914-1918 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - San Francisco alumni newsletters, 1915-1917 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - San Francisco alumni yearbook, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - San Francisco alumni chapter, report, constitution and misellaneous items (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Alumnus Alpha (San Francisco) newsletter, 1925-1930 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, A through Z, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, A through L, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, M through Z, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, A through Z, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1930s (non-specific date or name) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Recommendations to national office and letter from P. Cook, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Don Nugent, 1933, pertaining to his suggestions for reorganization on national level (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Evaluations of Grayson Kefauver’s “Evaluating the School Program” with a letter from Charles S. Morris, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Membership records, 1932-1933 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notification of election, 1925-1932 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Recommendations 1933 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous records, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Candidate forms, tests, etc., 1932 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Blank forms (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Minutes of national meetings and related correspondence, 1911-1933 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Report of the Executive Secretary to the 13th National Council of the Phi Delta Kappa Fraternity, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Minutes 1909-1917 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Minutes 1917-1923 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Minutes 1923-1929 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Minutes 1929-1932 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Minutes 1934-1937 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Constitution and Bylaws 1938, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Minutes 1938-1942 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Minutes 1943-1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Minutes 1947-1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Membership lists 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Minutes 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Minutes 1953-1956 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Receipts and disbursements 1924-1927 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Receipts and disbursements 1927-1930 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Receipts and disbursements 1930-1932 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Receipts and disbursements 1931-1934 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Receipts and disbursements 1933-1935 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Receipts and disbursements 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Receipts and disbursements 1940-1943 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Receipts and disbursements 1943-1948 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Stanford Journal of Phi Delta Kappa, 1923-1932 (incomplete) (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - The Delta Journal, 1932-1938 (incomplete) (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - The Delta Journal, 1939-1942 (incomplete) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Stanford News Journal, March 1967 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Research Studies in Eduction, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - “School District Reorganization,” The Phi Delta Kappan, March 1931 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Phi Delta Kappa Chapter Handbook, 1952 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - (Materials on national, district, and chapter organization; official documents; business procedures; publications and forms) (Box 8)
  - 24th Biennial Council, December 1953 (notebook of meeting materials) (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 24th Biennial Council, December 1953 (notebook of meeting materials) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 24th Biennial Council, December 1953 (notebook of meeting materials) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 26th Biennial Council, December 1957 (notebook of meeting materials) (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 26th Biennial Council, December 1957 (notebook of meeting materials) (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 30th Biennial Council, December 1965 (notebook of meeting materials) (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 30th Biennial Council, December 1965 (notebook of meeting materials) (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 30th Biennial Council, December 1965 (notebook of meeting materials) (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Phi Delta Kappa Directory, 1931 (Box 9, Folder 6)